Troy and Rutland Railroad Company; Records mss122
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
Troy and Rutland Rail Road Company Records
1814-1919
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
Troy and Rutland Rail Road Company
mss122
1.8 cubic ft. processed to date
The Troy & Rutland Rail Road Company Records contain legal and financial papers, board member correspondence, as well as voting certificates, ballot slips, & engineering drawings.
Access
Access to this record group is unrestricted.
Acquisition Information
All items in this record group purchased by the University Libraries, M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives, fromNew Englandiana on December 23, 1969.
Organizational Sketch
The Troy & Rutland Rail Road Company was a division of the much larger Rutland Railroad of Vermont. Although the Rutland operated for more than a century, the Troy & Rutland existed as such for only six of those years. Railroad historians have given detailed accounts of other Rutland rail lines, but extensive background on the Troy & Rutland remains elusive, perhaps due to the brevity of its existence.[1]
The Troy & Rutland was chartered on April 10, 1849, but financial issues prevented the start of construction until the following year, and it was not completed until early 1852. The T&R directors contracted with Barker, Sipperly, & Company to build what would become the southern portion of the Rutland Railroad's domain by connecting Salem Village (near the Vermont state line) to Eagle Bridge in Rensselaer, NY. From its inception, the Troy & Rutland had close ties with the Troy & Boston Co. as well as the Rutland & Washington. The latter played a pivotal role in the completion of the Troy & Rutland by helping to build trackline from Salem north to the Vermont line, resulting in a portion of track shared by the two companies which formed a continuous route up to Rutland. [2]
Upon completion, the railroad served dual purposes by transporting passengers and freight. Although the Troy & Rutland spanned less than 40 miles, it was part of nearly 400 miles of track operated by the Rutland Railroad, extending all the way up to Montreal. [2] The T&R had only just become fully operational when it was leased to the Rutland & Washington Railroad in July 1852 [3], eventually extending the latter's control entirely over the Troy & Rutland's trackline by 1855. Most records of the Troy and Rutland drop off sharply after that year. Although letters from the mid-1850s show interest in T&R track by the Albany Northern Rail Road, sources indicate that after the Rutland & Washington took over the Troy & Rutland, financier Jay Gould purchased many of the Rutland and Washington's bonds in 1857 [3]. The tracklines of both the T&R and the Rutland & Washington eventually became incorporated as the Troy, Salem, & Rutland Railroad by 1865 [4], only to fall under the auspices of the Delaware and Hudson Canal Company in the early 1870s [3].
Today, the distinctive green-and-gold livery of the old Rutland Railroad can still be seen via the Green Mountain Railroad, which has ties to the original Rutland & Burlington line. The Green Mountain Railroad offers scenic rides to tourists as well as freight service anywhere from six to seven days per week [5].
Scope and Contents
The Troy & Rutland Rail Road collection contains a variety of legal and financial papers as well as correspondence between board members and their colleagues. Legal documents include bond agreements, indentures, mortgage papers, and legal summons. Financial accounts include cost estimates, expenditures, and delivery receipts. There are several folders containing proxy voting certificates and ballot slips as well as one oversize box with engineering drawings. The collection also features miscellaneous items of interest such as a field book and several copies of the Troy Daily Whig. Correspondence has a wide range of senders and recipients including William Law, J.M. Stevenson, Bernard Blair, George Barker (of Barker, Sipperly, & Co.), bankers, and shareholders.
Box 4 is oversized and contains engineering drawings which are undated but would logically be circa 1850. Items are mainly loose papers plus one large, bound book. Drawings include several depot plans as well as land surveys and measurements for abutments and track line. Specifically mentions Foster's Bridge, Prospect Avenue, the Hoosic River, Owl Kill Bridge, the Batten Kill, and stations at Cambridge and White Creek.
The majority of the records in this collection would have been maintained by Troy & Rutland secretary William Law; however, his resignation as secretary in 1853 means that the records did come under the jurisdiction of other board members (including J.M. Stevenson, treasurer) from 1853 to 1855. One other exception is the Rutland Railroad logbook, which was acquired separately from the rest of the collection and deals with the parent company, the Rutland Railroad, in the early 20th century. Its keeper, railroad employee Ernest Reynolds, recorded which engines made trips on various days, where they went, and who the conductors were. Sometimes there are special notes, such as the one regarding the Lester Junction accident in which Reynolds broke his ankle. The log book covers April 1916 to May 1919. A black and white photograph of Reynolds was also acquired with the logbook.
Special Note: Items in Box 1, Folder 4 (Bound materials) are all folded and therefore very fragile-- assistance in handling will be necessary; some records may be unable to be viewed.
Special Note: Box 1, Folder 7 contains three letters that predate the T&R charter, one by thirty-three years and two by sixteen years. Despite the length of time that separates them from the charter in 1849, the letters make reference to the Troy & Rutland Rail Road as well as its president, Bernard Blair. William Law is also named as a letter recipient; uncertainty as to whether it is the same William Law who acted as railroad secretary from 1849-1853.
Arrangement of the Collection
The collection is organized into the following boxes:
All folders arranged alphabetically by subject.
Rensselaer County, New York; Railways; Business and Industry; Railroad companies; Troy & Rutland Rail Road Company; Troy (N.Y.); Rutland (Vt.); Minutes; Contract Documents; Voting Papers; Articles of Agreement; Drawings; Financial Records; Troy & Rutland Rail Road Company
- Box & Folder List, 1814-1919; Undated; 1; 1.8 cubic ft.
  - Articles of Association & By-laws, ca. 1850 (Box 1 (1-Box & Folder List), Folder 1)
  - Ballot Slips, ca. Undated (Box 1 (1-Box & Folder List), Folder 2)
  - Bond Agreements, ca. 1855 (Box 1 (1-Box & Folder List), Folder 3)
  - Bound Materials (Includes Troy Daily Whig, property table, bonds, poll lists, bids & estimates, tied up in cloth--various dates) (Box 1 (1-Box & Folder List), Folder 4)
  - Building Contracts, 1849 (Box 1 (1-Box & Folder List), Folder 5)
  - Building Contracts, 1850 (Box 1 (1-Box & Folder List), Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 1814; 1833; 1849-1852 (Box 1 (1-Box & Folder List), Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, 1853-1855; 1906 (Box 1 (1-Box & Folder List), Folder 8)
  - Cost Estimates, 1851 (Box 1 (1-Box & Folder List), Folder 9)
  - Delivery Invoices, 1851 (Box 1 (1-Box & Folder List), Folder 10)
  - Delivery Receipts, 1853-1878 (Box 1 (1-Box & Folder List), Folder 11)
  - Depositions, c. 1851 (Box 1 (1-Box & Folder List), Folder 12)
  - Director's Resolutions, 1849-1855 (Box 1 (1-Box & Folder List), Folder 13)
  - Expenditures, 1849-1855 (Box 1 (1-Box & Folder List), Folder 14)
  - Indentures, 1850-1852 (Box 2 (1-Box & Folder List), Folder 1)
  - Legal Agreements, 1850-1851 (Box 2 (1-Box & Folder List), Folder 2)
  - Legal Summons, 1852 (Box 2 (1-Box & Folder List), Folder 3)
  - Meeting Minutes *April 10, 1849 minutes contain copy of railroad charter*, 1849-1851 (Box 2 (1-Box & Folder List), Folder 4)
  - Meeting Minutes, 1852-1855 June (Box 2 (1-Box & Folder List), Folder 5)
  - Meeting Minutes Index, 1849-1855 (Box 2 (1-Box & Folder List), Folder 6)
  - Mortgage Papers, 1851 February (Box 2 (1-Box & Folder List), Folder 7)
  - Oath of Inspection, 1852 (Box 2 (1-Box & Folder List), Folder 8)
  - Poll List & Votes, 1855 (Box 2 (1-Box & Folder List), Folder 9)
  - Proxy Voting Certificates, 1851; 1852 (Box 2 (1-Box & Folder List), Folder 10)
  - Proxy Voting Certificates and Tallies, 1852 (Box 2 (1-Box & Folder List), Folder 11)
  - Proxy Voting Certificates and Ballot Slips, 1853 (Box 2 (1-Box & Folder List), Folder 12)
  - Proxy Voting Certificates, 1854 (Box 2 (1-Box & Folder List), Folder 13)
  - Proxy Voting Certificates and Ballot Slips, 1855 (Box 2 (1-Box & Folder List), Folder 14)
  - Reynolds, Ernest-- Logbook, 1916-1919 (Box 2 (1-Box & Folder List), Folder 15)
  - Reynolds, Ernest-- Photograph, Undated (Box 2 (1-Box & Folder List), Folder 16)
  - Shareholder Circular, Undated (Box 2 (1-Box & Folder List), Folder 17)
  - Stockholder's 1st Annual Report, Undated (Box 2 (1-Box & Folder List), Folder 18)
  - Survey Chart, Undated (Box 3 (1-Box & Folder List), Folder 1)
  - Travel Receipts, 1851 (Box 3 (1-Box & Folder List), Folder 2)
  - T&R Book of Levels, Undated (Box 3 (1-Box & Folder List), Folder 3)
  - T&R Field Book, Undated (Box 3 (1-Box & Folder List), Folder 4)
  - Engineering Drawings, c.1850 (Oversized 4)